<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Project on philippdubach</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tags/project/</link><description>Recent content in Project on philippdubach</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I Built a CGM Data Reader</title><link>http://localhost:1313/2025/01/02/i-built-a-cgm-data-reader/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/01/02/i-built-a-cgm-data-reader/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last year I put a Continuous Glucose Monitor (CGM) sensor, specifically the &lt;a href="https://www.freestyle.abbott">Abbott Freestyle Libre 3&lt;/a>, on my left arm. Why? I wanted to optimize my nutrition for an endurance cycling competitions. Where I live, the sensor is easy to get—without any medical prescription—and even easier to use. Unfortunately, Abbott&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/freestyle-librelink-us/id1325992472">FreeStyle LibreLink&lt;/a> app is less than optimal (3,250 other people with an average rating of 2.9/5.0 seem to agree). To their defense, the web app LibreView does offer some nice reports which can be generated as PDFs—not very dynamic, but still something! What I had in mind was more in the fashion of the &lt;a href="https://ultrahuman.com/m1">Ultrahuman M1 dashboard&lt;/a>. Unfortunately, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t allowed to use my Libre sensor (EU firmware) with their app (yes, I spoke to customer service).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My First 'Optimal' Portfolio</title><link>http://localhost:1313/2024/03/15/my-first-optimal-portfolio/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/2024/03/15/my-first-optimal-portfolio/</guid><description>&lt;p>My introduction to quantitative portfolio optimization happened during my undergraduate years, inspired by Attilio Meucci&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-540-27904-4">Risk and Asset Allocation&lt;/a> and the convex optimization &lt;a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~boyd/teaching.html">teachings of Diamond and Boyd at Stanford&lt;/a>. With enthusiasm and perhaps more confidence than expertise, I created my first &amp;ldquo;optimal&amp;rdquo; portfolio. What struck me most was the disconnect between theory and accessibility. Modern Portfolio Theory had been established since 1990, yet the optimization tools remained largely locked behind proprietary software.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Tech behind this Site</title><link>http://localhost:1313/2024/01/15/the-tech-behind-this-site/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/2024/01/15/the-tech-behind-this-site/</guid><description>&lt;p>Similar to how Simon Willison describes his difficulties managing images for his &lt;a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Dec/22/link-blog/">approach to running a link blog&lt;/a> I found it hard to remain true to pure markdown syntax but have images embedded in a responsive way on this site.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My current pipeline is as follows: I host my all my images in a R2 bucket and serve them from &lt;code>static.philippdubach.com&lt;/code>. I use Cloudflares&amp;rsquo;s image resizing CDN do I never have to worry about serving images in appropriate size or format. I basically just upload them with the highes possible quality and Cloudflare takes care of the rest.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>